Hi, my name is Ken and uh now we are
going to talk what's new in business
central 2026 release wave 2 for EDI and
e documents.
Uh so you already knows that we have e
documents functionality in our system
but we didn't have EDI before. What is
EDI itself? It is exchange of the order
information and other documents which
related to the order. So it's very
actual when uh you have buyer and seller
and they need to exchange information uh
what was uh in the purchase order what
was the response uh from the seller.
Yeah, such kind of things before as I
mentioned it was not possible to
exchange this information and now we
adding EDI functionality to the business
central.
Uh on this diagram it's a bit more
visible. So as I said we have a buyer
company and a seller company. buyer
creating a purchase order and they need
to share with the seller what they going
to order, which items, what quantity and
of course what is the expected dates. Uh
instead of sending email, they will be
able just to release the order and then
on the background it will generate the
e document which will be sent to the
seller. On the seller side, sales order
will be created automatically. Then
seller can accept or reject the order
and send a response back. Uh so buyer
will get a response where they will have
a status. So they will know what
happened with the order on the seller
side. when they post the purchase
invoice and open the pay uh payment
journal, they also will be able uh to
send a remittance advice file uh to the
seller side. So that's the flow which we
are currently covering. We have purchase
order document, sales order, order
confirmation, payment journal. E
document type is a purchase order, sales
order, order response and remittance
advice. And as I mentioned already, we
using uh the technology which we already
had in it. So we using our people uh
format and uh the solution is based on
the e documents themselves. So it's a
known technology behind the scene. Uh
the direction also you can see uh on the
slide. The good point here also that uh
you will be able to set up uh the
directions for the documents if it
should be only inbound or outbound or
both inbound and outbound. Uh now I also
want to mention some settings. It's
mostly the same as you had in the e
documents themselves. So you will need
to have the standard e document setup.
Uh then you will need of course to add
vendor and customer uh and set up them
to exchange um files electronically. Uh
you will need to use electronic
identifiers on both sides. Uh it is JN
or VT registration number. Uh for items
uh it's better to use the item reference
or jin. So then you will definitely have
the correct items on both sides. Um also
don't forget to put the quantity
delivery dates wherever you want to
exchange all the important information.
And yes, as I said, it is same pattern
as for the invoicing.
Uh, and we have the log for each
exchange. So, you will see which files
were created and how it went. Now, I
want to give a word to our engineer
Milita and she will demonstrate how it
works in business central.
Uh, thanks Cena. I'm Milita and now I'm
going to show you the ADI flow as a part
of E document. we will do it manually
and using ppple format. So uh the setup
is the standard e document configuration
and in both companies plus we need to
configure document types to export in
buyer company we need to uh add two new
document types purchase order and
remittance advice.
The process starts from buyer company
where we will create a new purchase
order.
We choose uh our vendor, insert
necessary information.
We will add some uh dates
and create two item lines.
We insert quantity
another one different item
with quantity too and we can also change
requested receipt date. Uh the next step
is releasing purchase order and the new
e document is automatically created and
linked to this purchase order. Uh with
new linkage functionality we can now
easily open the created document. So
from fact box we can move to e document.
Going to the logs we will export the
file and now we will move to the seller.
Uh we import XML file in inbound e
document list.
choose our ple format
and it automatically create sales order
in seller company. Also we can notice
that the new message acknowledgement has
been attached to this e document. We
will move to sales order and verify what
has been created.
We can see the dates are transferred.
We have two item lines with quantities
and amounts and also dates are transfer
as they were on purchase order.
Uh when we release sales order the new
message is created. We can also see it
from directly from the document and the
message is in accepted response type.
Now we will export this response.
We can verify it. We can see that as a
order reference ID is purchase order
document from buyer company and also
order response code is accepted.
And moving to buyer company we will
import order response. So we need to go
to a document list
and inbound list we will import
uh accepted response.
We choose purple format
and moving back to e document list. Uh
we have linked new accepted message as
our order response for our original
purchase order. The next step is posting
the purchase order.
We will post it and now apply payment
for it. We will go to payment journal.
create one payment for our vendor.
Insert some amount and apply the
invoice.
Then we need to send remittance advice
using our e document service
and then post the payment.
Once the payment is done and
application, we can go back to e
document list and see that we have now
the new remittance advice document and
checking the log
we got the new XML file for remittance
advice.
Um this represent uh exchange documents
uh through ADI uh inside e documents. So
we send purchase order to from buyer to
seller company. Uh then we automatically
create sales order and return order
response to the buyer. Uh the same e
document and message architecture has
been used for French regulatory feature.
So uh I'm going to show you we have it
introduces uh three new formats for
France.
The three new e document format for a
friend uh should be set upon e document
service and we set them as other
formats. So uh we have e reporting
people for reference and factox
regulatory life cycle events are stored
as messages and linked to original
invoice e document. So for example when
we apply customer payment uh the
collected um message has been created
while unapplying we creates uh negative
collected message. Uh other supported um
messages types are submitted, accepted,
refused and technical rejected. All of
these things allows um document
exchange, payment reporting, but also
regulatory status um tracking through e
documents.
Thank you for watching. Uh and we are
going to improve the mentioned
functionality. So see you in next wave.